<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research | Anıl Zenginoğlu</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/research/</link><atom:link href="https://anilzen.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Research</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Anıl Zenginoğlu</copyright><image><url>https://anilzen.github.io/media/sharing.jpg</url><title>Research</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/research/</link></image><item><title>Relativistic Perturbation Theory</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/research/perturbation-theory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/research/perturbation-theory/</guid><description>&lt;p>Historically, hyperboloidal compactification has been mainly considered by mathematical relativists. After the explicit construction of &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/content/publication/zengino%c4%9flu-2008-hyperboloidal/">hyperboloidal scri-fixing&lt;/a> and the demonstration of its benefits for &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/content/publication/zengino%c4%9flu-2008-tail/">scalar&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/content/publication/zengino%c4%9flu-2009-gravitational/">gravitational&lt;/a> perturbations, the method has become a useful tool with applications to many areas of black-hole perturbation theory, including the self-force and effective-one-body approaches to the binary black-hole problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project includes the following topics:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Astroseismology:&lt;/strong> Extend the applications of hyperboloidal foliations to stellar oscillations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Cosmological perturbations:&lt;/strong> Investigate relativistic perturbations of asymptotically de Sitter spacetimes using hyperboloidal methods.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Time-symmetric methods:&lt;/strong> Explore the application of unconditionally stable time-symmetric integrators to long-time evolution of black-hole perturbations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Massive fields at null infinity:&lt;/strong> Study the asymptotic behavior of massive scalar fields near null infinity by using hyperboloidal compactification.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Numerical Analysis</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/research/numerical-analysis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/research/numerical-analysis/</guid><description>&lt;p>The problem of outer boundary conditions for partial differential equations on unbounded domains has a long history that goes back to Sommerfeld. There have been significant developments in the treatment of artificial outer boundaries, particularly since the 1970s, with the rise and prominence of numerical methods. Such boundary treatments have various names, such as absorbing, complete, radiative, non-reflective, and transparent. We group them into two main categories: local and exact.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Local methods are convenient but approximate; exact methods are accurate but cumbersome.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Geometric intuition and computational experience suggest that &lt;strong>hyperboloical compactification&lt;/strong> is unique among the existing treatments of the outer boundary problem in the numerical literature: it is &lt;strong>local &lt;em>and&lt;/em> exact&lt;/strong>. In addition, the method leads to stable and efficient numerical implementations. This project will demonstrate these properties rigorously and provide guidelines for the optimal choice of free parameters in spacetime transformations.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scattering Problems for Engineering</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/research/scattering-problems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/research/scattering-problems/</guid><description>&lt;p>Wave propagation problems on unbounded domains are ubiquitous in computational mathematics, engineering, and technology, appearing in various domains such as ultrasonics, seismics, underwater acoustics, and electrodynamics. As a concrete example, consider the numerical computation of the radar cross-section of aircraft. Maxwell equations are solved numerically for the interaction of an incident electromagnetic wave with the aircraft.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-scattering-problem-for-an-aircraft-image-from-09113456httpsarxivorgabs09113456">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img src="./ka6d-arrows.webp" alt="Scattering problem for an aircraft" loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Scattering problem for an aircraft. Image from &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0911.3456" target="_blank" rel="noopener">0911.3456&lt;/a>.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The definition of the radar section involves the ratio of the scattered field to the incident field at the limit to infinity. The problem is posed on an unbounded domain. However, numerical computations typically replace the infinite solution domain with a finite numerical domain. The approximate radiation field is then measured just a few wavelengths away from the source based on rules of thumb. Obtaining higher accuracy requires either access to large spatial sections of the solution space, sophisticated extraction procedures, or near-to-far-field transformations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hyperboloidal compactification solves this problem efficiently. This project will demonstrate the applications of this relativistic method to scattering problems that arise in engineering and technology.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Nonlinear Einstein Equations for Gravitational Wave Astronomy</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/research/nonlinear-einstein/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/research/nonlinear-einstein/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the most important open problems with the hyperboloidal method is its application to the nonlinear Einstein equations for gravitational wave astronomy. The problem is that the compactification introduces formally singular terms that are numerically unstable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I proposed an approach for the &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2008-einstein/">&amp;ldquo;Hyperboloidal evolution with the Einstein equations&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> in 2008. The idea is to prescribe the conformal factor explicitly and choose a gauge that ensures the regularity of each of the formally singular terms. I had implemented this approach in spherical symmetry in my &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2007-conformal/">thesis&lt;/a> but the method was not sufficiently robust. I spent many years trying to improve the method but without success.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the recent years, Alex Vañó-Viñuales made &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.05384" target="_blank" rel="noopener">significant progress&lt;/a> on this problem. A related approach based on the &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1509.02071" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dual-frame formalism&lt;/a> is pursued by David Hilditch and collaborators.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I still consider the application of hyperboloidal compactification to a common formulation of the nonlinear Einstein equations as the most important open problem in the field. My goal in this project is to contribute to the solution of this problem. While this is a high-risk project, a successful implementation would lead to a breakthrough in the numerical computation of astrophysically relevant spacetimes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hyperboloidal Holography</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/research/hyperboloidal-holography/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/research/hyperboloidal-holography/</guid><description>&lt;p>The remarkable success of the hyperboloidal approach in representing propagating fields in the exterior of isolated systems suggests that it may be a useful tool for the study of quantum fields. In this project, I explore this idea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a certain sense, I argue that a choice of time provides a natural representation of physical fields. The geometry of space is hyperbolic. We live in one of Escher&amp;rsquo;s drawings representing hyperbolic space.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/research/hyperboloidal-holography/circle-limit_hu2734e20f410458ae3b7518ef99b78e48_83168_c80176fc41352676f8a36f2cb91c93ea.webp 400w,
/research/hyperboloidal-holography/circle-limit_hu2734e20f410458ae3b7518ef99b78e48_83168_ca3d6f258ed7205ba6eb2705560af8b4.webp 760w,
/research/hyperboloidal-holography/circle-limit_hu2734e20f410458ae3b7518ef99b78e48_83168_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_2.webp 1200w"
src="https://anilzen.github.io/research/hyperboloidal-holography/circle-limit_hu2734e20f410458ae3b7518ef99b78e48_83168_c80176fc41352676f8a36f2cb91c93ea.webp"
width="600"
height="600"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is clearly nonsensical heresy. Covariance under diffeomorphisms is a fundamental principle of general relativity. What does it mean that a certain choice of time is natural?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is the argument. The time evolution of certain physical observables does depend on foliation. For example, the ADM mass computed on Euclidean slices is constant under time evolution. The Bondi mass computed on hyperboloidal and null slices, however, decays due to radiation of energy to infinity. The Bondi mass is a more natural observable than the ADM mass.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consider a far away observer of a quantum system. In the mathematical idealization of this scenario, such an observer sits on future null infinity and &amp;ldquo;looks down&amp;rdquo; the null cone to observe the quantum system. The spacelike surface that this observer constructs as a surface of simultaneity will necessarily be hyperboloidal. Therefore, it seems reasonable to describe quantum fields on hyperboloidal surfaces.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In such a scenario, the idea that quantum fields are a bunch of harmonic oscillators goes away. Instead, we have damped oscillators with a complex term. Waves are stretched out towards infinity. Thereofre, a quantum wave in this description does not have a constant spatial wavelength, but its wavelength becomes unbounded as the field extends to the observer.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-holographic-principle">The holographic principle&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I recently noticed an interesting coincidence with the hyperboloidal description of spacetime. The spatial geometry of the Minkowski metric in hyperboloidal coordinates matches &lt;em>exactly&lt;/em> the spatial geometry of the Anti-de Sitter metric in standard coordinates. I wrote about this observation two years ago in a &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/post/hyperboloidal-holography/">blog post&lt;/a>. Back then, I thought this was a known curiosity, but there seem to be other advantages of this approach to holography. I&amp;rsquo;m now exploring this idea with the help of the NSF award. It&amp;rsquo;s more speculative than my usual work, but I&amp;rsquo;m excited to venture into this unfamiliar territory.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Numerical Optimization</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/research/numerical-optimization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/research/numerical-optimization/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>