<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Academic | Anıl Zenginoğlu</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/tag/academic/</link><atom:link href="https://anilzen.github.io/tag/academic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Academic</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://anilzen.github.io/media/icon_hu6b147281c14d31ddea9d4b1ec87dcb1f_1135_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>Academic</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/tag/academic/</link></image><item><title>Research Statement</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/post/research-statement/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/post/research-statement/</guid><description>&lt;p>Most of my research can be summarized as &lt;em>follow the light to infinity&lt;/em>. Below I explain these words in reverse order: infinity, light, follow.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="infinity">Infinity&lt;/h3>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Mathematics is the science of the infinite.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="float-right">Hermann Weyl (1930)&lt;/div>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;br>
&lt;p>You must have some familiarity with infinity if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this. Most of us think of the in-finite as that which does not end. There are many approaches to this intriguing notion and if you go down the rabbit hole, Weyl&amp;rsquo;s seemingly presumptuous assessment above starts making more sense. Infinity is everywhere in mathematics. Maybe you&amp;rsquo;ve wondered how space could end (what&amp;rsquo;s on the other side of the end?), or thought about &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/paradox-zeno/#AchTor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Achilles overtaking the tortoise&lt;/a> while you were racing your friends, or explained someone how you can fit infinitely many people infinitely many times into &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilbert%27s_paradox_of_the_Grand_Hotel" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hilbert&amp;rsquo;s Hotel&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But why would a physicist study it? All examples above are clearly mathematical constructs. Racers do overtake each other, and if a hotel is full you have to go find another one. After all, there is nothing &lt;em>truly&lt;/em> infinite in the physical world.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Infinity in physics is an excellent idealization in many circumstances. It is important here to make a distinction between &lt;strong>idealization&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>approximation&lt;/strong>. Our best physical theories are idealizations of the natural world. Given &lt;a href="https://www.maths.ed.ac.uk/~v1ranick/papers/wigner.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics in the natural sciences&lt;/a>, it is important to keep these idealizations in tact, instead of breaking them in approximations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The infinitely far is an idealization of a very large distance. Just like the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real_number" target="_blank" rel="noopener">real numbers&lt;/a> are more convenient than &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuzzy_number" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fuzzy numbers&lt;/a>, the infinitely far is more convenient than some arbitrary large distance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="light">Light&lt;/h3>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Henceforth space by itself, and time by itself, are doomed to fade away into mere shadows, and only a kind of union of the two will preserve an independent reality.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="float-right">Hermann Minkowski (1908)&lt;/div>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;br>
&lt;h3 id="follow">Follow&lt;/h3>
&lt;h3 id="highlights">Highlights&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I pioneered the use of horizon-penetrating, hyperboloidal coordinates in black hole perturbation theory &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2008-hyperboloidal/">[1]&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2011-geometric/">[2]&lt;/a> and performed the first numerical computations with such coordinates &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2008-tail/">[3]&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2009-gravitational/">[4]&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2010-asymptotics/">[5]&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I developed a practical method that solves the &lt;em>outer boundary problem&lt;/em> and the &lt;em>radiation extraction problem&lt;/em> in numerical calculations of wave equations &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2011-hyperboloidal/">[6]&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Together with Chad Galley, I computed the first global approximation of a black hole Green function in the time domain and explained the shape of caustic echoes from black holes by an optical effect discovered in 1890 &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2012-caustic/">[7]&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Together with Gaurav Khanna, I computed the first gravitational waves at null infinity on the background of a rotating black hole demonstrating an efficiency gain of at least 5000 in one simulation &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2011-null/">[8]&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Two of my papers published as part of the &lt;a href="https://www.black-holes.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Simulating-eXtreme-Spacetimes Collaboration&lt;/a> have been cited by the first detection of gravitational waves which led to the 2017 Nobel Prize in Physics &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/mroue-2013-catalog/">[9]&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/pan-2014-eob/">[10]&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="current-projects">Current Projects&lt;/h2>
&lt;h2 id="future-plans">Future Plans&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>Technology Statement</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/post/technology-statement/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/post/technology-statement/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>