<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Hyperbolic Geometry and Gravitational Waves | Anıl Zenginoğlu</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/nsf-award-2309084/</link><atom:link href="https://anilzen.github.io/nsf-award-2309084/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Hyperbolic Geometry and Gravitational Waves</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Anıl Zenginoğlu</copyright><image><url>https://anilzen.github.io/media/sharing.jpg</url><title>Hyperbolic Geometry and Gravitational Waves</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/nsf-award-2309084/</link></image><item><title>Research</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/nsf-award-2309084/research/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/nsf-award-2309084/research/</guid><description>&lt;p>The research projects for this NSF award are as follows.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/research/relativistic-perturbations/">Relativistic Perturbations&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/research/numerical-analysis/">Numerical Analysis&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/research/scattering-problems/">Scattering Problems for Engineering&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/research/nonlinear-einstein/">Nonlinear Einstein Equations&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/research/hyperboloidal-holography/">Hyperboloidal Holography&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I collect the publications supported by this award in a dedicated &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/category/nsf-award/">publication page for the NSF Award&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Education</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/nsf-award-2309084/education/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/nsf-award-2309084/education/</guid><description>&lt;p>The educational aspects of the award revolve around two objectives:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Develop a summer school on advanced numerical methods for solving wave equations using hyperboloidal foliations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Train a student in the interdisciplinary arts of numerical relativity and applied mathematics.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="summer-school">Summer School&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The summer school is an online, week-long event that I will hold in July 2024. The primary target for the summer school are advanced students in STEM programs in the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington%E2%80%93Baltimore_combined_statistical_area" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Washington–Baltimore Area&lt;/a>. I will particularly advertise the school in community colleges but it will be open to all interested students, at no cost, and available online. The school will be organized around a series of lectures, practical demonstrations, and hands-on coding sessions.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="student-training">Student Training&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The award will support a graduate student for two years. The student will pick a research project from the list of projects supported by the award. They will present their work at conferences, participate in the summer school, and publish their results in peer-reviewed journals.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- Ekrem Dağlıkoca is a PhD student in the [AMSC Program](https://amsc.umd.edu/) at the [University of Maryland](https://umd.edu). He is working with me on the computation of black-hole perturbations in cosmological spacetimes. He is expected to graduate in 2028. --></description></item><item><title>Community</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/nsf-award-2309084/community/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/nsf-award-2309084/community/</guid><description>&lt;p>A major objective that this award enables is building a community of researchers working with asymptotic methods in relativity. This is a relatively small community of geographically distributed but thematically focused researchers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During the years that I was out of active research, I worked as a coordinator of a similarly distributed research network in mathematical sciences on kinetic theory called &lt;a href="https://www.math.umd.edu/~tadmor/ki_net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KI-Net&lt;/a>. With this award, I will employ skills that I acquired during that time to build a community in my own field of research.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is a joint effort with David Hilditch, Rodrigo Panosso Macedo, and Alex Vaño-Viñuales.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="website">Website&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The community uses the aptly named website &lt;a href="https://hyperboloid.al" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hyperboloid.al&lt;/a>. All our events and activities are managed through this website. The website uses the &lt;a href="https://wowchemy.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wowchemy&lt;/a> research group theme; its source code is available on &lt;a href="https://github.com/anilzen/hyperboloid.al" target="_blank" rel="noopener">my GitHub page&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="workshops">Workshops&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The &amp;ldquo;inaugural&amp;rdquo; event of the community was the workshop &lt;a href="https://hyperboloid.al/event/copenhagen-23/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Infinity on a Gridshell&lt;/a>, held in July 2023 at the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niels_Bohr_Institute" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Niels Bohr Institute&lt;/a> in Copenhagen. The &lt;a href="https://hyperboloid.al/copenhagen-23-talks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">speakers&lt;/a> covered a wide variety of topics including black-hole perturbation theory, mathematical analysis of wave equations, and nonlinear Einstein equations. The workshop was a great success and we are planning to hold another one in 2024.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="topical-collection">Topical Collection&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We are planning to publish a topical collection in the journal General Relativity and Gravitation on the topic titled &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/collections/jjghbiafhc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;em>Hyperboloidal foliations in the era of gravitational-wave astronomy: from mathematical relativity to astrophysics&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. The guest editors for the collection are David Hilditch, Rodrigo Panosso Macedo, Alex Vañó Viñuales, and me. The collection will be open to all researchers working with hyperboloidal foliations. Submissions are accepted starting August 31, 2023.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For more information, please see the &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/collections/jjghbiafhc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">collection website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="virtual-seminars">Virtual Seminars&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We plan to initiate a series of virtual seminars starting September 2023. More information will be on our &lt;a href="https://hyperboloid.al" target="_blank" rel="noopener">website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>