<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>holography | Anıl Zenginoğlu</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/tag/holography/</link><atom:link href="https://anilzen.github.io/tag/holography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>holography</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Anıl Zenginoğlu</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 00:01:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://anilzen.github.io/media/sharing.jpg</url><title>holography</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/tag/holography/</link></image><item><title>Splitting Spacetime</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/post/2023/splitting-spacetime/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 00:01:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/post/2023/splitting-spacetime/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="predicting-the-future">Predicting the future&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Contrary to common belief, physicists are in the business of making predictions more than fortune tellers or astrologers. The hows and whys, the fundamentals and principles, &amp;ldquo;whether or not the world has three dimensions,&amp;rdquo; all boil down to one question: Can you predict the future?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Predicting the future for a physicist is, of course, a much more accurate undertaking than for fortune tellers, astrologers, or &lt;a href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/finance/news/wall-street-economists-consistently-wrong-171740454.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">economists&lt;/a>. We want to know what happens to well-defined variables describing the mathematical idealization of a natural system given a snapshot in time&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We call this process &amp;ldquo;solving an initial value problem.&amp;rdquo; We solve an equation of motion, typically a partial differential equation (PDE), with prescribed initial data. The PDE is the mathematical idealization of our model of the physical system under consideration. That&amp;rsquo;s where all the whys and hows go. The PDE describes how the chosen variables of the system vary in relation to each other. The initial data is the snapshot of these variables at a given time. The solution to this initial value problem is our prediction of the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The language of a snapshot in time distinguishes time and space. But didn&amp;rsquo;t special relativity teach us that time by itself and space by itself are mere shadows? Well, it did, and it didn&amp;rsquo;t. Special relativity taught us that the notion of time and simultaneity is observer-dependent. But time is still a special dimension in a relativistic spacetime, distinct from its spatial friends. You can already see at the level of the metric signature, $(-+++)$, that time is special.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To formulate an initial value problem, we need to split spacetime into space and time. In relativity, there are three approaches to splitting spacetime to formulate an initial value problem: Cauchy, characteristic, and hyperboloidal. Let&amp;rsquo;s take the flat, 1+1 dimensional spacetime to demonstrate these approaches. In standard coordinates $(t,r)$, the flat metric reads
$$ ds^2 = -dt^2 + dr^2 \tag{1} \label{1} $$
The most intuitive approach is to take the snapshot at $t=0$. The corresponding surface&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> is called a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cauchy_surface" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cauchy surface&lt;/a> and has specific desirable properties that generalize to more interesting cases. The associated &lt;a href="https://ems.press/books/esi/66" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cauchy problem&lt;/a> plays a central role in mathematical and numerical relativity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We also have null surfaces in relativity, named as such because they provide the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kernel_%28linear_algebra%29" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nullspace&lt;/a> of the metric \eqref{1} through $t\pm r$. This null cone is fundamental in many aspects. First, it determines the &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/spacetime-singularities/lightcone.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">causal structure of spacetime&lt;/a>. Second, it describes the propagation of disturbances. In particular, massless fields propagate along the null cone. Even before the advent of relativity, it was known that disturbances to solutions of wave equations propagate along these special surfaces called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Method_of_characteristics" target="_blank" rel="noopener">characteristics&lt;/a>. One can provide data on such characteristic surfaces and solve a &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.12942/lrr-2012-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">characteristic evolution problem&lt;/a>. This approach is particularly valuable in the modern era of gravitational-wave astronomy because gravitational waves are only defined at infinity along outgoing null directions.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="hyperboloidal-surfaces">Hyperboloidal surfaces&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The hyperboloidal approach is the odd one. You take a spacetime hyperboloid, say
$t^2 - r^2 = 1,$
and give initial data on the surface defined by
$t(r) = \sqrt{1+r^2}.$
This construction seems weird and arbitrary when you first encounter it. Why would you do something like this? How is this surface a &lt;em>snapshot&lt;/em>? Why not pick another transformation?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many relativists feel that hyperboloidal surfaces are somewhat unnatural, lacking the simplicity and elegance of the Cauchy or characteristic approaches. Below, I demonstrate how hyperboloidal surfaces extend the mathematical notion of a sphere to relativity and satisfy a physical principle, which, hopefully, is more intuitive for splitting spacetime into space and time. The concepts that we&amp;rsquo;ll encounter will lead us to speculations in the quantum realm.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mathematical-notion">Mathematical notion&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Hyperboloids as analogs of spheres in spacetime.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-a-spacetime-hyperboloid-times-up">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img src="./hyperboloid.png" alt="Hyperboloid" loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
A spacetime hyperboloid. Time&amp;rsquo;s up.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A circle is a set of points equidistant from a given point. This definition is among the purest in mathematics&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. To derive the equation for a circle, consider the Euclidean metric in two dimensions
$$ ds^2 = dx^2 + dy^2. $$
The set of points $\{x,y\}$ at distance $R$ from the origin satisfies
$$ x^2 + y^2 = R^2. $$
The circle (or sphere in three dimensions) is the simplest nontrivial example of a constant curvature surface, with its curvature being the reciprocal of its radius, $K=1/R$. Now, let&amp;rsquo;s consider the corresponding object in relativity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>What is the set of events equidistant from a given event?&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the relativistic setting, spacetime distance is proper time. Using the metric \eqref{1}, the set of events $\{t, r\}$ at proper time $T$ from the origin satisfies
$$ - t^2 + r^2 = \pm T^2. $$
This equation describes a spacetime hyperbola. The sign in the equation determines whether the hyperbola is spacelike or timelike&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. We&amp;rsquo;ll pick the negative sign for the spacelike hyperbola because we aim to construct a snapshot. I mentioned before that time is special, so let&amp;rsquo;s solve the above equation for time to obtain the future sheet of the spacelike hyperbola
$$ t(r) = \sqrt{T^2+r^2}.$$
This spacelike surface consists of points at proper time $T$ from the origin. Like the circle above, this surface has constant curvature, $K=1/T.$ The higher dimensional version of a hyperbola is called the hyperboloid.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We see that hyperboloids are the relativistic analogs of spheres. Hyperboloids are as natural in Lorentzian manifolds as spheres are in Riemannian manifolds.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="physical-principle">Physical principle&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Hyperboloids as analogs of soap bubbles in spacetime.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-a-soap-bubble-cluster-by-kym-coxhttpswwwkymcoxcomwork-statement-exhibitions">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img src="./featured.jpg" alt="Soap bubble cluster" loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
A soap bubble cluster. By &lt;a href="https://www.kymcox.com/work-statement-exhibitions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kym Cox&lt;/a>.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The circle has another attractive property: among all figures with a given area, the circle has the smallest perimeter. We&amp;rsquo;ve known this for over 2,000 years&lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. The corresponding statement for the sphere was only proven in the 19th century by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermann_Schwarz" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Schwarz&lt;/a>. Such optimization problems appear in many areas. One that is familiar to most people from early childhood is the soap bubble.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In mathematical terms, soap bubbles are minimal surfaces enclosing a fixed volume of air. The variational problem has the following action
$$ S = A - \lambda \cdot V. \tag{2} \label{2} $$
Minimize the area $A$ with the constraint that the volume $V$ is fixed. The mathematics of soap bubbles includes fascinating open problems with many &lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/monumental-math-proof-solves-triple-bubble-problem-and-more-20221006/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recent developments&lt;/a>. Frank Morgan, who proved the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_bubble_theorem" target="_blank" rel="noopener">double bubble theorem&lt;/a>, has a wonderful lecture on the topic.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CbpfpxOdUzU" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;br>
Here&amp;rsquo;s a particularly relevant quote from the lecture&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;If you want to understand the universe, start out by understanding the soap bubble.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Frank Morgan&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s try to understand the universe by understanding the soap bubble. We must first answer the following question as we did with the circle:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>What is the relativistic analog of a soap bubble?&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Formally, we can use the action for the soap bubble \eqref{2} and go one dimension higher.
$$ S = V - \lambda \cdot W. \tag{3}\label{3} $$
Now, the task is to &lt;em>maximize the volume&lt;/em> $V$ with the constraint that the &lt;em>spacetime volume&lt;/em> $W$ is fixed. In contrast to the soap bubble problem, we&amp;rsquo;re not looking for a minimal hypersurface in the relativistic setup but a maximal one. The minimal hypersurface would be null with vanishing volume.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s see the solution of this problem in a simple case. We compute the relativistic volume by integrating the square root of the determinant of the metric&lt;sup id="fnref:6">&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Denoting the determinant of the induced metric on the hypersurface by $h$ and the determinant of the spacetime metric by $g$, we have
$$ S = \int \sqrt{h}\ d^3x - \lambda \int \sqrt{-g}\ d^4x. $$
The extremization of this action leads to the requirement of constant mean curvature: $K = \lambda$, where $K$ is the trace of the extrinsic curvature&lt;sup id="fnref:7">&lt;a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. We&amp;rsquo;ll do this for the 1+1 Minkowski metric to find an explicit expression for the maximizer. We&amp;rsquo;re looking for an embedding, $t=t(r)$, that maximizes the action for the relativistic bubble. The induced metric is
$$ ds^2 = -dt^2 + dr^2 = \left(-t&amp;rsquo;^2 + 1\right) dr^2, $$
where $t&amp;rsquo;\equiv dt(r)/dr$. The volume from the origin to some radius $R$ is
$$ V = \int_0^R \sqrt{h} \ dr = \int_0^R \sqrt{1-t&amp;rsquo;^2}\ dr. $$
To calculate the spacetime volume, we need a reference surface. It turns out that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter which surface, so let&amp;rsquo;s just take the surface $t=0$. The spacetime volume is given by
$$ W = \int_0^R \int_0^{t(r)} \sqrt{-g} \ dt dr = \int_0^R t(r) dr. $$
Bringing these expressions together in the action \eqref{3}, we can read off the Lagrangian density
$$ \mathscr{L} = \sqrt{1-t&amp;rsquo;^2} - \lambda t. $$
The Euler-Lagrange equation for varying $t(r)$ with respect to the parameter $r$ reads
$$ \frac{d}{dr} \frac{\partial\mathscr{L}}{\partial t&amp;rsquo;} = \frac{\partial \mathscr{L}}{\partial t} \ \iff &lt;br>
\frac{d}{dr} \frac{t&amp;rsquo;}{\sqrt{1-t&amp;rsquo;^2}} = \lambda. $$
We integrate by $r$ and solve for $t&amp;rsquo;$ with the boundary condition $t&amp;rsquo;(0)=0$
$$ t&amp;rsquo;(r) = \pm \frac{\lambda r}{\sqrt{1+ \lambda^2 r^2}}. $$
By choosing the positive sign and integrating again, we get the equation for the spacetime hyperboloid
$$ t(r) = \sqrt{\frac{1}{\lambda^2} + r^2}. $$
We recognize the mean extrinsic curvature as $K=\lambda$ from our previous discussion on the relativistic analog of a circle. We now see that the hyperboloid is the relativistic analog of a soap bubble.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You may wonder what determines the value of the constant mean curvature. It&amp;rsquo;s the spacetime volume that we prescribe in the constraint. The larger the spacetime volume to be enclosed, the smaller the constant mean curvature. You can see this behavior in the Penrose diagram below. As I mentioned above, the reference surface doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter for the qualitative discussion. You can pick $t=0$ or $u=t-r=0$. The spacetime volume enclosed by the hyperboloid with $K=0.5$ is larger than the spacetime volume enclosed by the one with $K=2$ in both cases. The difference is shaded yellow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-smaller-curvature-k-corresponds-to-larger-spacetime-volume-irrespective-of-the-reference-surface">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img src="./tikz_figs/K_volume_t.webp" alt="Smaller curvature $K$ corresponds to larger spacetime volume irrespective of the reference surface." loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Smaller curvature $K$ corresponds to larger spacetime volume irrespective of the reference surface.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This behavior is actually very intuitive, as it&amp;rsquo;s the same for a soap bubble. The larger the volume of air that the bubble needs to enclose, the larger the bubble, and therefore the smaller the curvature of the bubble.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In summary, there&amp;rsquo;s a clear analogy between soap bubbles and hyperboloids. Soap bubbles are minimal surfaces enclosing a fixed volume of air. Hyperboloids are maximal surfaces enclosing a fixed volume of spacetime.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="quantum-foam">Quantum foam&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>What would the extremization of the action \eqref{3} mean physically? Does space arise from the extremization of spacetime bubbles?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It has been long predicted that spacetime shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be smooth at the Planck scale due to quantum fluctuations. It should be &amp;ldquo;foamy,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;bubbly,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;grainy,&amp;rdquo; or whatever you want to call it. Wheeler, the naming authority of theoretical physics, called this the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_foam" target="_blank" rel="noopener">quantum foam&lt;/a>. A foam is defined as a dispersion of bubbles, and we have just seen that the relativistic generalization of a bubble is a hyperboloid.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We arrived at the realm of speculation. We don&amp;rsquo;t know how to test the quantum foam idea experimentally. But we can imagine that quantum foam arises from quantum fluctuations of spacetime bubbles. The hypersurfaces that enclose those bubbles are hyperboloids. As usual, this mental image gives rise to further questions. What is the mechanism for the formation of such hyperboloids? How are they related to quantum fields?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One idea is that the hypersurfaces arise through entanglement. I&amp;rsquo;ve written about &lt;a href="../../hyperboloidal-holography/">hyperboloidal holography&lt;/a> before, where I argued that holographic entanglement entropy naturally extends to flat spacetime if we use hyperboloids as time slices. The variational principle suggests that these surfaces could also be useful in the context of &lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/in-new-paradox-black-holes-appear-to-evade-heat-death-20230606/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">quantum complexity&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These speculations open more questions than answers. Nevertheless, we now have a better sense that soap bubbles and their clusters may indeed provide a key to understanding spacetime.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img src="./foam.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>To be fair, not all physical theories focus on snapshots in time. There are theories formulated in terms of statistical ensembles, boundary value problems, or, as discussed in this post, variational principles. But there is a sense in which all these also arise from initial value problems under certain conditions.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ll sometimes refer to lines as (hyper)surfaces and circles as spheres. I&amp;rsquo;m demonstrating the mathematics in the simplest case with one spatial dimension, but the concepts generalize trivially to three-dimensional space.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>A fascinating &lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2022/05/16/the-mysterious-disappearance-of-a-revolutionary-mathematician" target="_blank" rel="noopener">story on Grothendieck&amp;rsquo;s life&lt;/a> mentions his first encounter with this definition as a twelve year old boy at an internment camp in France.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>Timelike hyperbolas describe observers with uniform acceleration, called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rindler_coordinates" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rindler observers&lt;/a>, and play an important role in quantum field theory in curved spacetimes, among others.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5">
&lt;p>This statement in a slightly different form was first asserted by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zenodorus_%28mathematician%29" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zenodorus&lt;/a>, who stated that a circle has a greater area than any polygon with the same perimeter. You can find a lovely account of the evolution of the isoperimetric problem &lt;a href="https://maa.org/sites/default/files/pdf/upload_library/22/Ford/blasjo526.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:6">
&lt;p>To understand how we compute volumes in relativity, read a bit about &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volume_form" target="_blank" rel="noopener">volume forms&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:7">
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not going through the general calculation here to avoid introducing lots of definitions, but the calculation itself is very short and can be found, for example, in the paper by &lt;a href="https://pubs.aip.org/aip/jmp/article-abstract/21/12/2789/444574/K-surfaces-in-the-Schwarzschild-space-time-and-the" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Brill, Cavallo, and Isenberg&lt;/a> from 1980.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Hyperboloidal Holography</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/post/hyperboloidal-holography/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 00:00:16 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/post/hyperboloidal-holography/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="brief-history-of-bekenstein-hawking-black-hole-entropy">Brief History of Bekenstein-Hawking Black-Hole Entropy&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When physicists want to understand something, they consider idealizations and extremes. To understand spacetime then, consider black holes.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The black holes of nature are the most perfect macroscopic objects there are in the universe:
the only elements in their construction are our concepts of space and time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subrahmanyan_Chandrasekhar" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Chandrasekhar&lt;/a> (1983)&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Black holes are simple with just two properties: mass and rotation. By dropping an object into a black hole, you can increase its mass and change its rotation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The simplicity of black holes contradicts the second law of thermodynamics, which states that &lt;em>total entropy never decreases&lt;/em>. If black holes are that simple, you can reduce total entropy by dropping a high-entropy object, say a hot teacup, into the black hole.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Archibald_Wheeler" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wheeler&lt;/a>, best known for coining the term &amp;ldquo;black hole,&amp;rdquo; tasked one of his graduate students at Princeton, the young &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_Bekenstein" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bekenstein&lt;/a>, with resolving this paradox. The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_general_relativity#Golden_age" target="_blank" rel="noopener">golden age&lt;/a> of relativity was in full swing around 1970, and Princeton was among the best places to be. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demetrios_Christodoulou" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Christodoulou&lt;/a>, another student of Wheeler, and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Hawking" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hawking&lt;/a> had just shown that &lt;em>the area of a black hole horizon never decreases&lt;/em>. To resolve the entropy paradox, Bekenstein conjectured that black holes must have entropy and that the entropy must be proportional to the area of the black hole horizon in Planck units. The proportionality constant was determined by the discovery of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawking_radiation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hawking temperature&lt;/a>, which is why we call it the &lt;a href="http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/Bekenstein-Hawking_entropy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bekenstein-Hawking&lt;/a> Black-Hole entropy
$$ S_{BH} = \frac{A}{4 L_P^2}$$
where $A$ is the horizon area, $L_P$ is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck_length" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Planck length&lt;/a>, $S$ stands for entropy (probably after &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_L%C3%A9onard_Sadi_Carnot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sadi Carnot&lt;/a>), and BH stands for &lt;a href="#brief-history-of-bekenstein-hawking-black-hole-entropy">Brief History&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You may think this is a curious result about curious objects called black holes with little relevance to our notion of spacetime. But consider the following question: what is the maximum entropy in a finite, say spherical region? If you take some high-entropy matter and squeeze it spherically (with your mind), eventually, you hit the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy, and the compressed matter forms a black hole. This thought experiment leads to the surprising conclusion that the entropy of any matter system is bound by the surface area of the smallest sphere that encloses it&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We started with black holes and arrived at the&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="holographic-principle">Holographic Principle&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Counterintuitively, the maximal entropy of a region scales with the area of its boundary, not its volume. The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holographic_principle" target="_blank" rel="noopener">holographic principle&lt;/a> pushes this area-dependence further, suggesting that the dynamics in a volume of space is encoded on the boundary of that space. In other words, the information content of a spacetime region is encoded on the surface of that region.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Take a break and think about this for a moment. How can our three-dimensional world be encoded on a two-dimensional surface? What does it mean? Is the universe a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simulation_hypothesis" target="_blank" rel="noopener">game&lt;/a> running on the screen of an alien child? Are we trapped in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Matrix" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Matrix&lt;/a>? Are we &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7nqcL0mjMjw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Livin&amp;rsquo; on the Edge&lt;/a>?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-aerosmith-livin-on-the-edge-video-1993">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Living on the Edge" srcset="
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/living_on_the_edge_hu173cdc4707bba8c72fbdcae6744ed276_37858_c7a240253d106fdf4dedfdaa3a7ac972.webp 400w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/living_on_the_edge_hu173cdc4707bba8c72fbdcae6744ed276_37858_207a77ccf2abf58e87d6f804fcaac0b9.webp 760w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/living_on_the_edge_hu173cdc4707bba8c72fbdcae6744ed276_37858_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://anilzen.github.io/post/hyperboloidal-holography/living_on_the_edge_hu173cdc4707bba8c72fbdcae6744ed276_37858_c7a240253d106fdf4dedfdaa3a7ac972.webp"
width="722"
height="531"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Aerosmith: Livin&amp;rsquo; on the Edge (Video 1993)
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="adscft-correspondence">AdS/CFT correspondence&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The most famous realization of the holographic principle is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AdS/CFT_correspondence" target="_blank" rel="noopener">AdS/CFT correspondence&lt;/a>. Conjectured by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Mart%C3%ADn_Maldacena" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Maldacena&lt;/a> in 1997, the correspondence suggests an equivalence between a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/String_theory" target="_blank" rel="noopener">string theory&lt;/a> in curved anti-de Sitter spacetime (AdS) and a strongly coupled &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conformal_field_theory" target="_blank" rel="noopener">conformal field theory&lt;/a> in a lower-dimensional flat spacetime. Aside from the details, the remarkable aspect of the conjecture is the duality between the bulk and the boundary of AdS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Below is a visual image for the AdS$_3$/CFT$_2$ correspondence. The cylinder represents the three-dimensional AdS$_3$ spacetime. On the boundary of the cylinder lives the 1+1 dimensional CFT$_2$. Slices of constant time are &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperbolic_manifold" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hyperbolic manifolds&lt;/a> with negative curvature, drawn as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poincar%C3%A9_disk_model" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Poincaré disks&lt;/a>. A gravity theory within the disks is dual to a gravity-free theory on the bounding circle. The boundary of space encodes the bulk.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-ads-is-hyperbolic-space-with-a-time-direction-wikimediahttpscommonswikimediaorgwikifileads3svg">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="AdS3" srcset="
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/AdS3_hu87bd1888389a6c14d9cc1117d0109a96_71192_61970cad7d4d717edc3a67b3ac88af73.webp 400w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/AdS3_hu87bd1888389a6c14d9cc1117d0109a96_71192_352cb1eb5025a0154dc7b8a7e0e7b971.webp 760w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/AdS3_hu87bd1888389a6c14d9cc1117d0109a96_71192_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://anilzen.github.io/post/hyperboloidal-holography/AdS3_hu87bd1888389a6c14d9cc1117d0109a96_71192_61970cad7d4d717edc3a67b3ac88af73.webp"
width="472"
height="480"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
AdS is hyperbolic space with a time direction. &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:AdS3.svg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wikimedia&lt;/a>
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The negative curvature of AdS is a feature and a bug. It allows the realization of the holographic principle due to its hyperbolic slices, but it also makes AdS an unphysical model for our universe. At cosmological scales, the universe has positive curvature and resembles de Sitter space. At astrophysical and smaller scales, isolated systems are modeled by asymptotically flat spacetimes. Either way, anti-de Sitter spacetime, with all its &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1611.01118" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bizarre&lt;/a> features, is not a good model for physical reality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Can we establish the holographic principle for isolated systems?&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="hyperbolic-hyperboloidal">Hyperbolic Hyperboloidal&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Consider the AdS$_3$ metric in static coordinates with curvature scale $L$
$$ ds^2_{\rm{AdS}} = - \left(L^2+r^2\right) d\tau^2 + \textcolor{RedViolet}{\frac{L^2}{L^2+r^2} dr^2 + r^2 d\theta^2},$$
Slices of constant time are hyperbolic spaces with negative curvature. Hyperbolic geometry has much more space near its conformal boundary than Euclidean space. It seems that flat spacetime with its Euclidean time slices and vanishing curvature would not allow such a description
$$ ds^2_{\rm{Mink}} = -dt^2 + dr^2 + r^2 d\theta^2 . $$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But now consider the time-shifted spacetime hyperboloid with curvature radius $L$
$$ (\tau-t)^2 - r^2 = L^2 $$
This hypersurface is spacelike everywhere and extends to null infinity. Such surfaces are called hyperboloidal. Solving for $\tau$, we choose the negative square root, so the surfaces extend to future null infinity.
$$ \tau = t - \sqrt{L^2+r^2}.$$
In this hyperboloidal time, Minkowski metric has hyperbolic spatial slices
$$ ds^2_{\rm{Mink}} = -d\tau^2 - \frac{2 r}{\sqrt{L^2+r^2}} d\tau dr + \textcolor{RedViolet}{\frac{L^2}{L^2+r^2} dr^2 + r^2 d\theta^2}. $$
Just like AdS, flat spacetime takes the form of hyperbolic space with a time direction. You can draw the spacetime geometry as a cylinder, which is what Penrose did in his first publication on conformal infinity in 1963.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-the-cylinders-in-penroses-drawing-are-hyperbolic-spaces-with-a-time-direction-penrose-prl-1963httpsjournalsapsorgprlabstract101103physrevlett1066">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Penrose cylinder" srcset="
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/featured_hu7eb71e76e4f9e823419f039672d26a8d_30573_5c28c60ce0a2024da2163000044e7e0a.webp 400w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/featured_hu7eb71e76e4f9e823419f039672d26a8d_30573_dd8192eb1d14d6f9877e737a76389855.webp 760w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/featured_hu7eb71e76e4f9e823419f039672d26a8d_30573_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://anilzen.github.io/post/hyperboloidal-holography/featured_hu7eb71e76e4f9e823419f039672d26a8d_30573_5c28c60ce0a2024da2163000044e7e0a.webp"
width="377"
height="365"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
The cylinders in Penrose&amp;rsquo;s drawing are hyperbolic spaces with a time direction. &lt;a href="https://journals.aps.org/prl/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevLett.10.66" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Penrose, PRL (1963)&lt;/a>
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The agreement of the geometry of hyperboloidal and AdS slices is suggestive. Calculations in the AdS/CFT literature performed on time slices may carry over to flat spacetime in hyperboloidal coordinates. One such example is the Ryu-Takayanagi conjecture.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="rt-if-you-agree">RT if you agree&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Ryu and Takayanagi (RT) have &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/0603001" target="_blank" rel="noopener">proposed&lt;/a> a relation between geometry in AdS and entropy in CFT.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One can interpret the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy as a measure of information lost to external observers. The black-hole horizon acts as a screen dividing space into two subsystems inside and outside the horizon. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entropy_of_entanglement" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Entanglement entropy&lt;/a> is proportional to the area of this screen. The RT conjecture relates the entanglement entropy on CFT to the surface area of a screen in AdS that divides the AdS boundary into subdomains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Words don&amp;rsquo;t do it justice, so let&amp;rsquo;s look at a picture. Below is a diagram from the &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/0603001" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RT paper&lt;/a> for AdS$_3$ /CFT$_2$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-diagram-demonstrating-rt-proposal-on-ads_3cft_2-ryu-and-takayanagi-arxiv-2006httpsarxivorgabshep-th0603001">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="RT conjecture" srcset="
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/RT_diagram_huc187e2868a67d5cdf87ff9d98ee019fe_90520_3d67cdaa312f19f9d0c16a749eafda23.webp 400w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/RT_diagram_huc187e2868a67d5cdf87ff9d98ee019fe_90520_d2c76ec2eb6abc02b8c34de0f7348e36.webp 760w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/RT_diagram_huc187e2868a67d5cdf87ff9d98ee019fe_90520_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://anilzen.github.io/post/hyperboloidal-holography/RT_diagram_huc187e2868a67d5cdf87ff9d98ee019fe_90520_3d67cdaa312f19f9d0c16a749eafda23.webp"
width="760"
height="487"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Diagram demonstrating RT proposal on AdS$_3$/CFT$_2$. &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/0603001" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ryu and Takayanagi, arXiv (2006)&lt;/a>
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The two subsystems $A$ and $B$ of CFT$_2$ live on the boundary of AdS$_3$. They are separated by a screen $\gamma_A$ required to be an extremal surface in the bulk AdS$_3$. An extremal &amp;ldquo;surface&amp;rdquo; on a slice of AdS$_3$ is a geodesic line connecting the meeting points of the domains $A$ and $B$ on the bounding circle. The RT proposal states that the entanglement entropy of subsystem $A$ is proportional to the area of the screen $\gamma_A$:
$$ S_A \sim \rm{Area\ of\ }\gamma_A $$
In this case, we are talking about the length of a geodesic on a time slice. You can easily see that the calculation does not change whether you are in AdS or hyperboloidal Minkowski. In the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryu%E2%80%93Takayanagi_conjecture#Example" target="_blank" rel="noopener">example on Wikipedia&lt;/a>, the AdS$_3$ metric is written in the spatial coordinate $\rho$ defined through $r=\sinh \rho$, so
$$ ds^2_{\rm{AdS}} = -\cosh^2\rho\ d\tau^2 + \textcolor{Blue}{d\rho^2 + \sinh^2\rho\ d\theta^2}. $$
The same spatial geometry is obtained in hyperboloidal coordinates in Minkowski&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>
$$ ds^2_{\rm{Mink}} = -d\tau^2 - \sinh\rho\ d\tau d\rho + \textcolor{Blue}{d\rho^2 + \sinh^2\rho\ d\theta^2}. $$
This flat metric describes a stack of hyperbolic disks, just like the AdS metric. The length of the geodesic and its relation to entanglement entropy are the same in hyperboloidal coordinates. The original RT proposal applies directly to flat spacetime!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The RT proposal reveals an interesting interpretation for the area dependence of entropy. It is easier to understand that entanglement entropy should be proportional to the area of a screen and not to the volume behind it. But maybe we should ask first: What is volume?&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="thinking-outside-the-ball">Thinking outside the ball&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When we think of volume, we typically envision a box or a ball and consider the space inside. Relativity modifies our intuition about space and time, so it is reasonable that our notion of volume is modified as well. The volume of a region $B$ is the integral of the volume form
$$ V_B = \int_{B} \sqrt{\det h} \ d\Sigma, $$
and depends on the spatial metric $h$. In flat space we have $\sqrt{\det h} =$ $r^2 \sin\theta$. The volume of a ball of radius $R$ gives us the usual formula that we memorize at school
$$ V_{B(R)} = \int_{0}^{R} \int_0^{\pi} \int_0^{2 \pi} r^2 \sin\theta \ dr d\theta d\varphi= 4\pi \int_{0}^{R} r^2 dr = \frac{4\pi}{3}R^3. $$
For the hyperboloidal foliation with $L=1$ we have
$$ h = \frac{1}{1+r^2}dr^2 + r^2 d\theta^2 + r^2 \sin^2\theta d\varphi^2,\quad \sqrt{\det h} = \frac{r^2 \sin\theta}{\sqrt{1+r^2}}. $$
The volume expression changes to
$$ V_{B(R)} = 4\pi \int_{0}^{R} \frac{r^2}{\sqrt{1+r^2}} dr. $$
We can get a sense for it using Taylor expansions. For small spheres with $R \ll 1$, we get the usual result
$$ V_{B(R)}=\frac{4\pi}{3}R^3+O(R^5).$$
For large spheres, however, the series expansion for $R\gg 1$ gives
$$ V_{B(R)}=2\pi R^2 + O(\ln R).$$
Remarkably, volume and area scale the same way near the asymptotic boundary in hyperboloidal coordinates.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These are suggestive observations about the potential usefulness of hyperboloidal surfaces in holography. And indeed, there is a current effort using hyperboloidal surfaces for holography.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="celestial-holography">Celestial Holography&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In the context of quantum gravity, the holographic principle suggests duality between a gravity theory in the bulk and a quantum theory on the boundary. &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.02075" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Celestial holography&lt;/a> suggests that asymptotically flat spacetimes are dual to a theory living on the &amp;ldquo;celestial sphere&amp;rdquo; at infinity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The theory uses Bondi coordinates along null infinity to discuss asymptotic symmetries, and switches to a hyperboloidal slicing to discuss massive particles. The slices they use have been first proposed as a cosmological model by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milne_model" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Milne&lt;/a> in 1935. Milne slices are level sets of
$$ \tau^2 = t^2 - r^2.$$
Introducing the spatial coordinate
$$ \rho = \frac{r}{\sqrt{t^2-r^2}}, $$
the Minkowski metric takes the form
$$ ds^2_{\rm{Mink}} = -d\tau^2 + \tau^2 \left( \textcolor{RedViolet}{\frac{1}{1+\rho^2} d\rho^2 + \rho^2 d\sigma^2}\right). $$
Again, we recognize the representation of Minkowski spacetime as a stack of hyperbolic disks. But in this case, the metric coefficients depend on time $\tau$. And the mean extrinsic curvature of Milne slices vanishes asymptotically in time as $K=3/\tau$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I suspect that the hyperboloidal foliation we discussed &lt;a href="#hyperbolic-hyperboloidal">above&lt;/a> is better than Milne slicing for holography. Consider the Penrose diagram of Milne slices.
&lt;figure id="figure-penrose-diagram-of-milne-slicing-strominger-arxiv-2017httpsarxivorgabshep-th0603001">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Hyperbolic slices" srcset="
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/hyperbolic_hu07438a4e6e3cb093e518d73c9c90a40d_74988_db8958ccf0594bed0168ca2fed9d8f85.webp 400w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/hyperbolic_hu07438a4e6e3cb093e518d73c9c90a40d_74988_67332c32c03e6a61abc8f80af55f0e95.webp 760w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/hyperbolic_hu07438a4e6e3cb093e518d73c9c90a40d_74988_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://anilzen.github.io/post/hyperboloidal-holography/hyperbolic_hu07438a4e6e3cb093e518d73c9c90a40d_74988_db8958ccf0594bed0168ca2fed9d8f85.webp"
width="444"
height="453"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Penrose diagram of Milne slicing. &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/0603001" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Strominger, arXiv (2017)&lt;/a>
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
The Penrose diagram and the metric reveal some undesirable features of Milne slices compared to the hyperboloidal foliation:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The slices intersect at null infinity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The coordinates are time-dependent.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is no analog of the AdS curvature scale.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In contrast, the hyperboloidal foliation has constant mean curvature, $K=3/L$, playing the same role as the curvature scale in AdS geometry. The coordinates are independent of time and provide a smooth foliation of null infinity. Below are Penrose diagrams for such hyperboloidal, constant-mean-curvature foliations with different values of the mean extrinsic curvature, which acts as a dial between characteristic and Cauchy surfaces.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-penrose-diagrams-of-hyperboloidal-foliations-with-different-mean-extrinsic-curvatures-k632-zenginoğlu-arxiv-2008httpsarxivorgabs07124333">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Hyperboloidal foliation" srcset="
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/hyperboloidal_huddf2caadb7366214d7f4d1665843ed97_102448_3b2e6e1d322650da3e63826c855b461a.webp 400w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/hyperboloidal_huddf2caadb7366214d7f4d1665843ed97_102448_f6ff2e6e1abd3e3ba1c347060783a487.webp 760w,
/post/hyperboloidal-holography/hyperboloidal_huddf2caadb7366214d7f4d1665843ed97_102448_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://anilzen.github.io/post/hyperboloidal-holography/hyperboloidal_huddf2caadb7366214d7f4d1665843ed97_102448_3b2e6e1d322650da3e63826c855b461a.webp"
width="760"
height="338"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Penrose diagrams of hyperboloidal foliations with different mean extrinsic curvatures $K={6,3,2}$. &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0712.4333" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zenginoğlu, arXiv (2008)&lt;/a>
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Milne coordinates have one advantage that a hyperboloidal foliation of null infinity cannot provide. A massive particle in constant motion will asymptote to a point on the Milne slices. Dirac used this property in his 1949 paper on &lt;a href="https://journals.aps.org/rmp/abstract/10.1103/RevModPhys.21.392" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Forms of Relativistic Dynamics&lt;/a> and it appears repeatedly in celestial holography. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how important this is. But Milne coordinates are also hyperboloidal. So in that sense, celestial holography is already using hyperboloidal holography.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Celestial holography is relatively new and developing rapidly. We don&amp;rsquo;t know how the final version will look like. That&amp;rsquo;s the excitement of research.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="wrap-up">Wrap up&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>A few curious observations suggest that hyperboloidal coordinates are interesting for holography.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Flat spacetime becomes a stack of hyperbolic disks, with a &lt;a href="#hyperbolic-hyperboloidal">cylinder&lt;/a> representing the global picture.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The original &lt;a href="#rt-if-you-agree">Ryu-Takayanagi calculations&lt;/a> apply to Minkowski spacetime.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#thinking-outside-the-ball">Volume scales as area&lt;/a> near the conformal boundary.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Spacetime hyperboloids are essential in &lt;a href="#celestial-holography">celestial holography&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Are these observations indicative of a profound duality, an underlying realization of the holographic principle for isolated systems in hyperboloidal coordinates? I don&amp;rsquo;t know. The similarity between Minkowski in hyperboloidal coordinates and AdS is interesting, but it can also be misleading.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The observations here are, by their very nature, coordinate-dependent. Suitable coordinates may ease calculations and suggest research directions, but the results should not depend on them. A significant, coordinate-independent difference to the AdS case is the null conformal boundary of asymptotically flat spacetimes. Any realization of the holographic principle will need to incorporate the null boundary and the associated &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bondi%E2%80%93Metzner%E2%80%93Sachs_group" target="_blank" rel="noopener">symmetries&lt;/a> as celestial holography is attempting to do.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It can be misleading to take similarities in specific coordinates too far, but it can also be a missed opportunity to ignore them. I think hyperbolic geometry and hyperboloidal surfaces will keep playing an essential role in holography. &lt;a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Watch%20this%20Space" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch this space!&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;script src="https://giscus.app/client.js"
data-repo="anilzen/anilzen.github.io"
data-repo-id="MDEwOlJlcG9zaXRvcnkzNzExMzY1Njk="
data-category="General"
data-category-id="DIC_kwDOFh8YOc4CTAsV"
data-mapping="pathname"
data-strict="0"
data-reactions-enabled="1"
data-emit-metadata="1"
data-input-position="top"
data-theme="dark"
data-lang="en"
data-loading="lazy"
crossorigin="anonymous"
async>
&lt;/script>&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>There are various subtleties here that I&amp;rsquo;m glossing over. You can go down the rabbit hole following the &lt;a href="http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/Bekenstein_bound" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bekenstein bound&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>Setting the curvature radius to unity for simplicity, $L=1$.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>