<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research | Anıl Zenginoğlu</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/category/research/</link><atom:link href="https://anilzen.github.io/category/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Research</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://anilzen.github.io/media/icon_hu6b147281c14d31ddea9d4b1ec87dcb1f_1135_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Research</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/category/research/</link></image><item><title>How far is infinity?</title><link>https://anilzen.github.io/post/empirical-infinity/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anilzen.github.io/post/empirical-infinity/</guid><description>&lt;p>Most of my research uses infinity in numerical computations. When presenting my work, I often encounter the objection that infinity is not physical. But not all infinities are created equal, and some are more physical than others. We can &lt;strong>verify by experiment&lt;/strong> that we are at infinity with respect to distant sources of radiation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Below I collect some thoughts on infinity and describe the experiment. Feel free to skip my ramblings and go directly to the &lt;a href="#a-thought-experiment">experiment&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="we-dont-need-no-infinity">We don&amp;rsquo;t need no infinity&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Physicists are generally uncomfortable with infinity. First, it is argued, infinity cannot be the outcome of a physical experiment. Second, infinity as the outcome of a calculation indicates problems with the theory. Resolving such problems is important because they reveal interesting research directions such as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renormalization" target="_blank" rel="noopener">renormalization techniques&lt;/a>. Since infinity doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense in experiment and should be avoided in theory, physicists are skeptical when it appears in mathematical descriptions of physical phenomena. A few examples: Max Tegmark argues that infinity is an idea that should be &lt;a href="https://www.edge.org/response-detail/25344" target="_blank" rel="noopener">retired from physics&lt;/a>; Nicolas Gisin aims to &lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/does-time-really-flow-new-clues-come-from-a-century-old-approach-to-math-20200407/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">understand time&lt;/a> without relying on infinitely precise numbers; And here is a quote from &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41567-018-0238-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The physics of infinity&lt;/a> by Ellis, Meissner, and Nicolai:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>We maintain that in each physical case where $\infty$ is used in a discussion, greater insight is attained by considering what large number $N$ will suffice instead because real physics is embodied in that number.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This uneasiness of physicists with infinity is also present in mathematics. There are mathematical philosophies and formalisms without infinity, such as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finitism" target="_blank" rel="noopener">finitism&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intuitionism" target="_blank" rel="noopener">intuitionism&lt;/a>. I was attracted to similar ideas when I was in college, so I went down the rabbit hole of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuzzy_number" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fuzzy numbers&lt;/a>. They seemed like a &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; way to represent physical measurements, which are not real numbers with infinite precision but fuzzy numbers with uncertainties. The more I learned about fuzzy numbers, however, the less I was convinced of their general utility. They seemed rather cumbersome and did not improve calculations in most cases. I learned, by way of fuzzy numbers, that successful mathematical representations do not necessarily match our physical intuitions. The map is not the territory.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We should use the most powerful mathematical tools that give us the best quantitative description of our measurements. That&amp;rsquo;s why we should keep infinity around.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="empirical-infinity">Empirical infinity&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Aristotle distinguishes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actual_infinity" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two notions of infinity&lt;/a>: actual and potential. Potential infinity is what children learn first: numbers just keep going &amp;ldquo;forever&amp;rdquo;. Actual infinity is the completion of this process: the set of all numbers as a mathematical object.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We do not observe infinity directly but we use it to represent our impressions of the natural world. For example, in projective geometry, the point at which two parallel lines meet is at infinity. In a painting, you may see both sides of a road meet at a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vanishing_point" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vanishing point&lt;/a>. The road ends somewhere but the painting suggests that the meeting point is beyond the horizon of perception. The representation of &amp;ldquo;far&amp;rdquo; on the canvas is infinity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The infinity on the canvas is neither potential (it&amp;rsquo;s a finite, completed representation of infinity) nor actual (the horizon is actually at a finite distance). Let&amp;rsquo;s call it empirical infinity. Empirical concepts are abstracted from individual perceptions. Infinity is the best canvas representation of your perception looking down a long, seemingly unending road. You don&amp;rsquo;t know how far you can see, and you don&amp;rsquo;t care about representing that particular detail in your painting. You just want to express that it&amp;rsquo;s very far.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="a-thought-experiment">A thought experiment&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Black hole perturbations have a property that is different at infinity and at a finite distance&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Let&amp;rsquo;s use this property to determine where we are with respect to the black hole. We would need very accurate gravitational wave detectors to measure this property, which we don&amp;rsquo;t have yet, so consider this a reasonable thought experiment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Perturbations of a black hole go through an oscillatory period, and subsequently decay with a power-law $ \sim 1/t^p$, where $t$ is time as measured by the observer and $p$ is the decay rate&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Surprisingly, the decay rate $p$ is different depending on where you observe the perturbations: at finite distances it&amp;rsquo;s 3, at infinity it&amp;rsquo;s 2. The slower decay rate at infinity is somewhat unexpected. One could argue that the power-law decay, which was first discovered for finite distances, should be non-radiative, in the sense that it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be detected at infinity. As demonstrated by Gundlach, Price, and Pullin in 1994, it is not only radiative but even decays slower than at finite distances&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. There are explanations of this slower decay in terms of accumulation of backscattering off of curvature towards infinity, but this is not our main concern. Given that the rates at finite distances and infinity are different, we ask the following question:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Which decay rate would we observe?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The answer determines whether infinity is the appropriate model for our relation to the source of radiation. Let me now explain why we would observe the decay rate at infinity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Below is a figure from a &lt;a href="https://anilzen.github.io/publication/zenginoglu-2008-tail/">paper of mine&lt;/a> where I studied various decay rates. The figure shows the evolution of the decay rate in time for various distances.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure id="figure-decay-rates-in-time-at-various-distances-from-the-source">
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Decay rates by distance" srcset="
/post/empirical-infinity/featured_hucb430a8324f06a774b153a0b9634005a_69007_817f95dc0fad8e4ebf7e82021c91590b.png 400w,
/post/empirical-infinity/featured_hucb430a8324f06a774b153a0b9634005a_69007_3099d79d982491e0ef9c365b36e83eda.png 760w,
/post/empirical-infinity/featured_hucb430a8324f06a774b153a0b9634005a_69007_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w"
src="https://anilzen.github.io/post/empirical-infinity/featured_hucb430a8324f06a774b153a0b9634005a_69007_817f95dc0fad8e4ebf7e82021c91590b.png"
width="711"
height="440"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;figcaption>
Decay rates in time at various distances from the source.
&lt;/figcaption>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The long-time decay rate is 3 for any finite distance. But initially, the decay rate for distant observers is much closer to 2 than to 3. The top curve in the figure is the measurement at infinity, and the next closest curve is at 40,000 units of black hole mass (in these units, a solar mass corresponds to a distance of 1.5 km). For a small black hole of 5 solar masses, this observer is about 300,000 km away. This may sound far away, but it&amp;rsquo;s just one light second; about the distance between the Earth and the Moon. To compare, typical sources of gravitational waves are thousands and millions of light years away.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If we ever get to measure the power-law decay from black-hole perturbations, we will measure the infinity value and not the finite distance value, even though we are a finite distance away from the sources. Given that the distances are literally astronomical, it&amp;rsquo;s more practical to use infinity both in our calculations and in our discussions where it&amp;rsquo;s needed, instead of artificially avoiding it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="wrap-up">Wrap-up&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I think most people agree that actual infinity doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist in the real world. But the number 3 also doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist in the real world. Numbers are useful concepts abstracted from observations and represented in mathematical models. The decay rate experiment demonstrates that infinity is a useful concept in describing astrophysical observations. We should embrace empirical infinity and its appearance in our formalisms as long as it improves our calculations.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- &lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet">&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr">Hugo 0.15 will have 30%+ faster render times thanks to this commit &lt;a href="https://t.co/FfzhM8bNhT">https://t.co/FfzhM8bNhT&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/gohugo?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#gohugo&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/golang?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#golang&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://t.co/ITbMNU2BUf">https://t.co/ITbMNU2BUf&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&amp;mdash; Steve Francia (@spf13) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/spf13/status/666616452582129664?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 17, 2015&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8">&lt;/script>
-->
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>The observation of a radiative field at infinity gives the part of the field that falls off as $1/r$. In other words, for a radiative field $\phi$, its observation at infinity is $\lim_{r\to\infty} r \phi$.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>This was first discussed in detail by Richard Price in his 1972 paper &lt;a href="https://journals.aps.org/prd/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevD.5.2419" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nonspherical Perturbations of Relativistic Gravitational Collapse. I. Scalar and Gravitational Perturbations&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>C. Gundlach, R. H. Price, and J. Pullin. &lt;a href="https://journals.aps.org/prd/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevD.49.883" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Late-time behavior of stellar collapse and explosions. I. Linearized perturbations.&lt;/a> Physical Review D 49.2, 883 (1994).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item></channel></rss>